[SPEAKER_01]: This is just a small section in the Majjhima Nikaya 77.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is the ten kasiṇas.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says, I have proclaimed to my disciples the way to develop the ten kasiṇas.
[SPEAKER_01]: One contemplates the earth kasiṇa, above, below, across, undivided and immeasurable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just do the first one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And thereby, many disciples of mine abide having reached the perfection and consummation of direct knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's earth, water, fire, air, colors, blue, yellow, red, white, space, inconsciousness, kasiṇa.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kasiṇa, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kasiṇa literally means totality.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the meaning of the word kasiṇa.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I think even in Sanskrit, it's the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: The totality, the extent, something.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it only occurs in, I think, a couple of the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I think it was mostly, like, later interpretations, kind of took on the whole practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And today, when people hear kasiṇa, they think about staring at the clay disks, or balls filled with water.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even the Buddha himself says, you contemplate.
[SPEAKER_00]: You develop, you establish your mind upon it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like establishing your mind upon a certain greater extent, the greater totality, from the totality that your mind dwells on to day-to-day level, which is pretty much totality of sensuality, totality of ill-will, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when we talk about developing, eh... discerning the greater context peripherally and then maintaining that in your mind through your own sati and mindfulness, not forgetting it, that's already practicing that established mind upon a better totality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because totality means it unifies whether you are turning left, right, forward, backward, up, down, doesn't matter which direction you take, it's all within certain totality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why I'm broken immeasurable.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm broken by your choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm broken by your directions and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if your mind is established, like, for example, in terms of the context that people can relate to, establish your mind upon the context of sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't matter then.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you want the sensuality, if you don't want sensuality, if you're barely restraining, if you're unsuccessful in your restraint, the value, the totality of the value of sense restraint remains there, held up by you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you still have at least a chance, then, to return to it and start, well, and align your behavior correctly to that, to that totality of that value.
[SPEAKER_00]: The context.
[SPEAKER_00]: The context, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the worst if you abandon the totality of the value of sense restraint, and then, even if you don't necessarily engage with sensuality, you're not valuing freedom from it, and you will... thus, you will never make sufficient effort to free yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you maintain that totality as unbroken value, even if you necess... like, imperfect in your sense restraint in the beginning, you can eventually perfect it, because the totality remains there as an anchor point, as a reference point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why, similarly, in other suttas, when the Buddha said, the monk who is withdrawn from village, from the crowd, lives in seclusion, solitary life in the forest, his mind establishes himself upon the perceptions of the forest.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he recognizes any perceptions that would come on account of inferior village life, that would bother somebody, cannot bother me, because my mind is established upon the perception of the forest.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where I dwell.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if something were to happen to the forest, I would be disturbed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if somebody comes and starts cutting trees and destroying that forest, his perceptions would then go.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, his mind would not be established because the totality is gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, he recognizes that liability.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, he reflects thus.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, what if I were to establish my mind upon even a greater totality that cannot be destroyed easily?
[SPEAKER_00]: The totality of earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because earth is the totality that's in common to the forest and the village and in between and the city, wherever you might be.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the problem for people, like, is when you hear this, it's just too abstract to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, the idea of worth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that idea doesn't stand for anything in their experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's because their experience hasn't been cultivated sufficiently enough, so that they can discern the element of worth within their experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when I say cultivated sufficiently enough, means unbroken sīla developed sufficiently enough, sensory strength dedicated to sufficient enough, mindfulness cultivated sufficiently enough, right views developed sufficiently enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, it will be just an abstraction that you will then sort of mystify and fantasize and equate with staring at a clay ball somehow, like, will take your mind into the magical dimension of the totality of earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You contemplate the extent of earth, the extent of solid, which is in common to me, you, village, mountains, everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: The factual, the facticity of your body, if seen rightly, reveals the element of earth, the great earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: You've seen rightly the element of water, the totality, not the actual, physical, particular thing you focus on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all these totalities are on the level of peripheral and even more peripheral, if your mind can take it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the atmoskāsina, the most refined kāsina, as the Buddha would say, is the one of consciousness, which is the ultimate peripheral of the negative presence, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Negative, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's nothing substantial to consciousness, but even that can be discerned by the mind that has developed to such an extent of that peripheral perception, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's the same beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: That context that we talk about peripherally, that's the direction of any samādhi, any jhāna, any mind development, any casino establishment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why if you cultivate it, you abandon anything inferior that your mind would be focusing on and picking on, and nothing inferior can bother you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you want to actually... maybe here's an example that can illustrate this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Think about it like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: You live in the village or the city and you have your day-to-day worries and happiness and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your life revolves around it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't really see the greater totality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And suddenly, you find out on the news there is a massive comet heading and it's gonna... there's a good chance it might wipe the entire planet Earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: The greater totality than the one you live in, specifically where you're focusing and attending and choosing, how quickly would all of your village worries disappear and got replaced by a greater worry?
[SPEAKER_00]: The totality of... and that's exactly the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to upgrade your totality, not through focusing and staring at various things that you might believe represent on, by actually contemplating and discerning it as already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: The totality of experience in the village or city or home or lay life or whatever else is within the totality of an enduring earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Already.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what if I were to scare you on account of that totality?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, everything inferior would stop bothering you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you would get replaced by that bother.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what if you were to then overcome the fear in regard to the totality of earth?
[SPEAKER_00]: How could you then possibly be afraid on account of anything that comes from the village?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't even care what happens to the earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: If that comment hits it or not, you're equanimous on that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing in video that comes through your senses can bother you anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have surmounted it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even a putujana can discern these totalities and use them to abandon sensuality and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: What they cannot see, without a right view, is how to relate rightly to that totality.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is useful to abandon.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like sometimes when people even like, you know, like have a have a notion of God or a divine and they use it to transcend this world.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, the sensuality and everything else, because... but the relationship between them and the totality of God, or whatever they call it, that's... has no understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why they're still putujan, they're still liable to rebirth and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then the Buddha said, but the target that teaches not just the totality that you can find and use to abandon inferior things that might bother you, as in upgrade your context, even as a lay person that's not interested in practice, you'll be more beneficial to upgrade your context and not just be absorbed and narrowed down to what's right in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Find a greater totality and maintain your mind on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the Tāgata teaches, then, the understanding, the gratification in regard to totality, the danger, the escape.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, the Buddha used the same description as he used for, like, abandoning centrality and other unwholesome states, how to abandon the casinos.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what differentiated him.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, like, a man might establish himself upon the element of earth,
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... because of that, he would abandon everything inferior to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he cultivates his mind on that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a good cultivation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not necessarily wisdom of the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, obviously, he's abandoning lots of dust.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if he were to hear the Buddha's teaching, he wouldn't need much of an instruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that teaching would be, now, the way you abandon everything inferior, understood it as impermanent, unsatisfactory, turn the same reflection to that Earth because of which you abandon everything inferior, to that totality of Earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Remove your emotional connection to the, I need this Earth in order to be alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Become equanimous on that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you would have understood the extent of the gratification in earth, the danger in earth, the escape in earth, and the path that leads the way to escape the earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, he goes on to describe the same principle for all the ten casinos.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't matter how peripherally your mind can, like, is developed or can develop.
[SPEAKER_00]: What matters is to keep, basically, rehearsing and drilling the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Discern a greater totality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Develop a greater context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, even maraṇasati, in a way, mindfulness of death, has a unifying totality to everything you experience in this life.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basically practice of casino, even if it's not specifically the topic of the of the casino.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you were to take up a context, cultivate it, and then that context in itself, see it as a reason against your will, not in your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have no say in it, if it comes or goes or disappears.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you use it to abandon your attachment and your infatuation with objects of your senses, concerns of your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, one of the prerequisites for entering jhāna is basically abandoning concern and worry in regard to the world, in regard to basically the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to have been withdrawn first, sufficiently enough, long enough, and then the mind will start discerning this greater totality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, jhāna is another form of totality practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, your mind establishes upon greater totality, that in itself is free from greed, aversion, delusion, and it's wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why puthujjana cannot attain jhānas as well, without the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need the right view to establish your mind in that principle of that totality.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you need a form of establishment of your mind in the principle of totality in order to get the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, some people will need more of it, some people will need less of it, depending on how, you know, quick and well-versed your mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, nevertheless, some form of samādhi, in that sense, is needed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like citta samādhi... cittanimitta is already a form of... it's a precursor to samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's already a form of samādhi from Kuntujana's point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Composing a greater context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's another totality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Presence of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mood is always there, regardless of how you specifically feel, or what you're specifically doing, or what you might be doing, what you're worried, what you want to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a certain container of the mood always enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you recognize, it doesn't matter if the mood is good, or bad, or neutral.
[SPEAKER_00]: The weight of the mood is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That becomes your totality.
[SPEAKER_00]: That becomes your context, that now you're maintaining.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by maintaining the clarity in regard to it, you're basically discerning the characteristics of that mood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it endures.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not maintaining it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're liable to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, the weather endures.
[SPEAKER_00]: It affects the directions and so on, but neither of that needs to be the basis for you being affected and burdened by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only time you're burdened by it is when your mind falls from that totality and gets absorbed into things that are being pressured by the mood, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, element of earth means the element, the element of solid.
[SPEAKER_00]: The greater totality that partakes in, doesn't matter how specific and particular things are, or how general they are.
[SPEAKER_00]: The earth is there, enduring, as a necessary basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: The consciousness is there, enduring, as a necessary basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: Practically speaking, the feeling is there, enduring, as a necessary basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when other suttas, they would have said, feeling is the point of converging.
[SPEAKER_00]: The experience converges on feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, feeling is the basis for convergence of any kind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's framework.
[SPEAKER_00]: When we spoke about in other talks, way of establishing mind upon the creative framework, totality, creative context, it's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, when you hear about casinos or something, you approach it as another, oh, another thing I focus on, a clay pot, or a thing filled with water, or a candle flame, and you see how far removed that is from the actual direction where casinos are.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you will become mystified because it's fundamentally abstract, because people cannot relate to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no basis for relating to it or getting the right idea.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you were to cultivate the general context, the peripheral context in regard to your current experience, and always keep that peripheral eye upon yourself, even when you are focusing on things, that's already closer to what the actual casinos are, even if you don't specifically think in terms of casinos.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, like, that's already the nature of nimitta, nature of the sign, signs and tokens of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, even if you see a sign, stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: The command to stop, to stop moving your body, to not cross this line, is not in the sign.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sign is literally a shape, red and white text.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you're perceiving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, you are seeing the meaning behind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even when people are doing the focusing practices and so on, you still cannot escape the meaning.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can only keep yourself oblivious to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even when you're staring at things, your thoughts are there, giving the significance to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just not seeing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you think through staring or focusing, you're somehow going to have a magical release.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's what nimitta is already.
[SPEAKER_00]: The meaning behind things that you perceive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Signs and tokens, the significances.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when the Buddha gave the simile of nimitta, it was like the cook.
[SPEAKER_00]: Two cooks, they cook for a king, and one cooks various dishes and pays no attention to
[SPEAKER_00]: These are basically, kind of, preferences that King will exhibit through his behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: He will not say, I like this, I don't like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he will take six scoops of this, and only one of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, you infer, you discern the sign, based on what you perceived, of taking this, not taking this, as meaning he likes that.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sign that King likes that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the other doesn't discern that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the one that doesn't discern those signs gets fired.
[SPEAKER_00]: The one that discerns it, he gets promoted.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's the same the monk who discerns the signs of his own mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: When he attends to this, what signs manifest?
[SPEAKER_00]: What meaning is shown?
[SPEAKER_00]: What rises?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it sensuality, non-sensuality?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it ill-will or non-ill-will?
[SPEAKER_00]: If he pays no attention to what's behind, he will not progress in the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even that, see, it's abstract for many people.
[SPEAKER_00]: You say nimitta, and they think these glowing lights and flowering nimitta signs and projections and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's literally signs and tokens of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: The nimitta of the recorder, the nimitta of the book, the nimitta of the robe, what it means, what it represents, what it stands of, all are forms of nimittas.
[SPEAKER_00]: And yes, you look at the objects that are agreeable to the eye, there are nimittas, meaning of it, that are basically enticing, pulling you towards sensuality,
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you could also discern wider nimittas, wider significances that require a bit more effort to establish that the danger, peril, entrapment, all of the unwholesome, in the same thing you perceive in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Does the Buddha say, the monk who wants to practice mindfulness, he doesn't attend to the nimittas of enticing nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: He attends to the nimittas that would result in dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And those are not these things that are kind of perceived in the... Beautiful remains beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're still seeing the same beautiful thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nimittas are not in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's already... that's already... like, I'm talking about this because that's already the principle of that... of any mind development that includes kasiṇa as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: The nimitta, the significance of... of certain necessary basis of solidity, of earth, presence of element of earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: If there are no things in the world, there would be no perception in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't matter how far that... how far removed that might sound, abstractly, it's still the most, like, obvious fact, even, like, if your body is not there, as this sort of semi-solid lump, you would not be able to think, perceive, feel, like, dislike, be upset, happy, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: The necessity of physical body, the necessity of the element of Earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why often, basically, like rūpa, the word rūpa was used for form, matter of any kind and for the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's your first point of matter that you experience is your own body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any other matter you experience is just basically experiencing the matter of your body that experience the matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot perceive things with your eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: You basically perceive your eyes seeing things.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you see, even on a day-to-day level, how much that's forgotten, lapsed from people's context.
[SPEAKER_00]: You forget that your senses are objects in the world that you have no control over, they will wither and die.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you genuinely are fully absorbed in the sense objects, fully repelled by them, as if there is no basis of your senses that enables you for either of those.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, saḷāyatana, it's already a form of totality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And actually, yātana means that, means base, means the extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fields as well, sometimes was translated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the practice of kasiṇa is the practice of that peripheral establishment upon things that we unify both here and there and my sense objects, my sense organs and sense objects and everything in between.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether I perceive this in the city, perceive that, whether I'm happy on account of what I perceive here, or what I perceive over there, if Earth is under threat, everything would be devalued, because now I have a greater body, that unifies, includes me, and the village, and the city, and the things that I like, and things that I dislike.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, just abandon the worry in regard to it, but don't abandon that peripheral context, that you do depend on the randomness of the planet Earth, the winds, the change, the earthquakes, all this, all this.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's another reflection the Buddha gave in another sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if this great Earth is an unchanging mountains and so on, if they are liable to change, which they are, what is to be said about this pathetic little body?
[SPEAKER_00]: And you experience this passion through the recognition of obvious nature that you've been ignoring before, because you haven't had the context that even this great totality of earth is liable to change, and earthquakes, and shakes, and disintegration, and heat, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Destruction, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Form deforms.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I am based on that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you are within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if form of that great kind, great totality, deforms,
[SPEAKER_00]: How can I have the slightest notion that I want, or I shouldn't, or I'd be affected when I do?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why the Buddha said to those monks, like, oh, would you be upset if people come and start breaking these twigs and branches around us in this woodland?
[SPEAKER_00]: They said, no, because, you know, who gives?
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody gives any care about these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you should regard your own body.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, like, if it were to be broken, destroyed, you should not be emotionally affected.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, look, these Mount Himalayas are eroding.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what is to be said about this soft, little, tiny lump of flesh?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only reason why it doesn't stick with people is because they don't invest enough effort to maintain it on the level of the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let it endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, like, let it endure and protect it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, like, it's like simmering fire that's starting heating you up, basically, more and more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eventually, the heat will accumulate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you have that anxiety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: What if the earth, what if the world is to disappear?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it will.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, what if?
[SPEAKER_00]: It will.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you use that concern to become equanimous in regard to that concern on that level of the element of earth, planet of earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, nothing will bother you of the inferior nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's easier to... seemingly easier, not in the long run, but on the immediate level, it's easier to not look there and not experience that anxiety, but instead, choose to focus and absorb and fully absorb yourself in the objects of your senses, with the belief that that will somehow reveal the great truth behind and that will free you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just basically, you want more of the sensuality, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's what sensuality does.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's full absorption with the sense object.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fully forgetting about the necessary basis of your senses, the necessary basis of your enduring pathetic little body, and all you see is the sense object, and you're fully, kind of, in passion with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So now, your meditation doesn't go to those sense-objects, but takes another sense-objects of staring, hearing, feeling, touching, touching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Getting an image in the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Getting images and visions in the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like... it's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're pretty much expecting, hoping for the same results.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will result in the culmination of the great pleasure of enlightenment and nirvana.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you want to develop kasiṇa, start developing peripheral awareness, mindfulness, context and clarity.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you'll see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, the mind will then start being established upon the greater totality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you extend that totality to the element of earth, element of cohesion, element of heat, element of the presence, element of space, yeah, conserve that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That light, that would reveal any different colors, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, like, Sariputin, that, I don't know, Sutta... Oh, no, maybe it was Maha Moggallon, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: One of the top monks at the time, it was the same log in front of him, and he was seeing it as earth, as water, as fire, as air.
[SPEAKER_01]: The same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: As beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: As beautiful, as ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how versed, in all these extents, he was.
[SPEAKER_00]: He could just pick them.
[SPEAKER_00]: He could just pick them peripherally, in regard to the same attending log that he's attending to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not he's looking at different things and forgetting about the law.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's exercising there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, he's basically cultivating the discernment, that he was able to...
[SPEAKER_00]: Developing his mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: He has discerned the element of cohesion that unifies anything that appears in your experience, your feeling, your thoughts, perceptions, internally, externally, internally and externally.